Hello, welcome back to Arya Nagarjuna,
class number 15.
We were reviewing these chapters
that we were going through
because we were trying to
get a picture of the flow
of all the chapters, which
we didn't get when we were
focusing on individual hard ideas.
And so we were talking about...
We're talking just now
about somebody complaining
to Arya Nagarjuna and saying,
"Well, if these things don't
exist from their own side
"then why didn't Buddha say that?
"And why did he say things
did exist from their own side
for a long time?"
And then Arya Nagarjuna has
pointed out that they...
And as our audience said here...
Who was that?
It depended on the students.
It's just up to the what students he had.
It's very interesting that Choney Lama
before he moves on to the next topic,
he goes to something that
is a big favorite of ours,
which is... Tim, the next picture!
"The Diamond Cutter Sutra."
And I love...this is
very famous, this is the
"The Diamond Cutter Sutra"
in Chinese, the oldest
dated book in the world
with a date inside of it,
which I think is 880AD.
And why we brought it up
here is that Choney Lama,
who wrote the great commentary
to "Diamond Cutter Sutra,"
which you should buy online as an e-book
from Diamond Cutter Press,
because it just came out.
It's on his mind. It's on
Choney Lama's mind. And he says,
"By the way, while you're on the subject
"of complaining about what
Buddha said or didn't say,
"do you remember in the
Diamond Cutter Sutra,
he says Buddhas don't teach."
Yes, he said, "Don't complain to me,
"Buddha said Buddhas don't teach.
"Don't complain about the content,
"complain about the fact he said
I shouldn't be teaching at all."
And again, of course, that
means that as we know,
as we've talked about many
times, when you read this sutra
or any other sutra, actually
what's happening is your
mind is projecting the
words down on a blank page
and in a way you can say you're the author
of "The Diamond Cutter Sutra."
Does that mean you understand
it? Not necessarily.
Well, how can I be writing a
book that I don't understand?
Karma expands 100% every day.
You figure out the numbers.
What's interest rate? It's
like a million or something,
I don't know.
So, there is a famous statement
in "The Diamond Cutter Sutra",
that when the Buddha
teaches they don't teach.
And what that means is
when the Buddha does teach,
that's coming from you.
All right, we said there
were five big topics
in the 'me' and 'mine' stuff.
Here's the third one.
DE KHO NA NYID LA BKRI BA'I RIM PA,
which means they get
into a small discussion
of what's the best way for us
to teach other people these ideas.
And that got into some different ideas
about the meaning of the word 'pure'.
BKRI here B-K-R-I,
means when it comes time for us
to teach other people emptiness
then what are his suggestions?
And he basically says the same thing.
He says, "Teach them
according to their capacity
and don't go over their capacity."
Fourth step about examining me and mine
is that it's called
DE KHO NA NYID KYI MTSAN NYID,
which means what are the main...
I always think of a nice car.
Seiji's just bought a
Tesla which I'm looking at,
because it's so pretty.
I just don't know if I want to sit on
two tons of electromagnetic
cancer... Anyway.
DE KHO NA NYID KYI MTSAN NYID,
means when you're selling a Tesla you say,
"Look it's got this beautiful front end,
"and it's got this navigation system.
"It's got special brakes, like
when you let off the brakes
"they put on the brakes, and
stuff like when you go around
"a curve and you let off the gas,
"it puts on proportional braking.
So you kind of only drive with one foot."
So anyway, those are the
selling points of the car.
Those are the cool things about the car.
He says, "Hey you want
to know the cool things
"about emptiness?
Let me tell you the selling
points of emptiness."
And that's the fourth
main topic here called,
DE KHO NA NYID KYI MTSAN NYID,
which means, "I'll give you some
selling points for emptiness"
and the verse is very important,
the verse is very famous.
You got this verse?
GZHAN LA...
Yes, boy, there was a big
a mistake in the Tibetan.
Not the input operators, it was
a mistake of the carver. But
I'm going to just read this
to you because is very famous.
,GZHAN LAS SHES MIN ZHI BA DANG,
,SPROS PA RNAMS KYIS MA SPROS PA,
,RNAM RTOG MED DON THA DAD MIN,
,DE NI DE NYID MTSAN NYID DO,,
Last line says DE NI
DE NYID MTSAN NYID DO,,
means, "Hey you want to
know the big selling points
for emptiness?"
Which here he calls,
DE NYID, which is tatva,
which means suchness.
Let me give you the main
selling points for suchness.
And then he says, it's an amazing list.
GZHAN LAS SHES MIN means no one...
It's not something you can
learn from somebody else.
Then Geshe-la, why everyday of the year
you're sitting here talking
about emptiness, making videos?
It cannot be communicated
so directly that a person
sees emptiness right
after you talk to them.
It's not possible. It never happens.
Well, it almost happens.
But it never happens
that you can meet someone
who saw emptiness directly and say,
"Look just give me five
minutes, let's sit down,
you just tell me what
you saw and that's it."
And he says, "No", GZHAN LAS SHES MIN
It's not something that you can learn
from another person immediately.
They need to teach you over, over, over
and then you'll have the experience.
ZHI BA...
And I'm going to define this
different selling points.
There are five of them:
five Tesla's selling points.
The first one is,
GZHAN GYIS BSTAN PA TZAM
LAS DNGOS SU SHES PA MIN GYI
You cannot have the direct experience
just by listening to someone
describe it, even a direct experience.
GNYIS SNANG LOG PA'I
TSUL GYIS MTHONG DGOS PA
You must work on your habit
of misunderstanding where
things come from. That's all.
You have to work on the
pen, work on the pen.
Then it will be communicated to you.
But no matter how much a
person would love to sit down
and describe it to you, it's not possible.
It just never happens.
You don't have that many seeds.
First selling point, which
is kind of a negative thing
for me.
You can't learn it just by listening
to someone for 10 minutes.
It's not going to happen.
Second, then it says 'peace',
and then you're like,
"Oh, if I study emptiness
I will enjoy my life.
"I'll always sit around
on my couch and feel good
even without Netflix,"
which is almost inconceivable.
But 'the peace' here
is not the peace that means to feel good.
The peace here as a selling
point of emptiness is death,
rest in peace.
RIP. Rest in Peace.
This SHI BA means killed, dead.
SHI BA in Tibet means dead.
ZHI BA means peace.
But he says, "This peace is,
NGO BO NYID KYIS ZHI BA".
The second selling point for
emptiness is that it is peace
in the sense that there's no
war going on inside the bottle,
of thinking it comes from itself.
It doesn't mean OMmmmmmmmm...
It doesn't mean that.
It means the state of
this bottle is peace.
Why?
It doesn't have a war inside.
Why? It doesn't have a self nature.
And it never had a self nature.
GDOD MA NAS ZHI BA
It is peace from the
beginning of no beginning.
It was always peace. It
never had self-existence.
You made the war. You put the war here.
It was peace, meaning it
didn't have the war of thinking
it was self-existence.
That's cool. Peace from
its own side, self-peace.
Well, that's illegal also.
All right, number three.
DON DAM PAR SPRO BAR BYED
PA'I NGAG GI SPROS PA RNAMS
KYIS MA SPROS PA STE MA BRJOD PA DANG,
How do we say this? When
you experience it directly,
it's not with concepts.
When you experience it directly
you're not talking in your head.
It's a direct communion.
It's a direct communion
with ultimate reality.
SPROS PA means...
Prapañca means there is no blah blah
going on in your head.
It's a direct experience.
It's free of that kind of blah blah.
SPROS PA means constructs,
mental constructs.
Number four,
RNAM RTOG GI RGYU BA RNAMS MED
means when you talk about
the qualities of emptiness,
an important one is RNAM RTOG.
RGYU BA means racing through your head.
It also the word for car race, horse race,
RGYU BA...
and RNAM RTOG GI RGYU BA
means you're not just...
How do you say?
You don't have blah blah
thoughts going on in your mind,
but sometimes blah blah thoughts
means thinking that the
thing from its own side.
So that's tricky, here. All right?
Number five,
CHOS THAMS CAD KYI DE KHO
NA NYID RIGS MTSUNGS PAS
DON THA DAD PA MIN PA STE
Every object in the universe
is as empty as any other object
and anyone who sees
emptiness once directly,
sees it as well as
anyone ever did or will.
A Buddha doesn't see emptiness
directly better than an Arya
for the first time. It's 100%.
It's totally 100%.
Then that's that idea that you can't have
the decrease of emptiness.
There can't a 40% mouse not
in the kitchen or something.
Either it there or it's not there.
If it's not there it's 100% emptiness.
If you see emptiness directly
at age 20 or something as a human being,
you see it exactly the
same way as Buddha does,
no different. It's interesting.
Those are selling points.
Having discussed the
features that emptiness has,
he goes into a little bit
about the features that things
don't have and the picture was keystroke.
Yes, and I keep talking
about seeds and sprouts,
but the number of friends I have
who really understand gardening is one.
I mean, we don't grow things.
When I was a kid I honestly
believed that watermelons,
sandia, came from the back of the store.
I thought that.
I thought they made them
in the back of the store.
So we don't live in an
agricultural society,
it's like the Bible, right?
We don't live in a society
where we do much growing things,
but we do keystrokes.
So to think that when your finger
comes down the screen changes,
to believe that...
Choney Lama does a cute thing,
he says, "You know what?
Nagarjuna is jumping
"from the five qualities
that emptiness does have,
to the one quality that nothing has."
And isn't that cool? So he's
seeing a connection where
maybe he's making it up in
a way, but aren't we always?
He's like, "Here's the five
great features of emptiness
"but, by the way, there's things you think
are features of things that aren't."
Like what? Like thinking
that you make the letter
on the screen by hitting
the key with your finger.
Hitting the key with your finger
doesn't bring the letter on the screen.
That's how we would say it nowadays.
That connection between keystroke
and something changing on
the screen is not natural,
which you will discover
whenever your computer breaks.
You make lots of keystrokes
and nothing happens.
That connection is not natural.
That's also coming from
you and it can wear out,
and then your computer breaks.
And then you're pissed off
because you lose half your stuff.
Fifth major section of this chapter.
DON DE NGES PAR BSGRUB
DGOS PAR BSTAN PA'O,,
He says, "Don't just study
emptiness. Do something."
BSGRUB DGOS means 'do something'.
You've got to do something.
Don't just study emptiness.
Now you got to do something with it
and he's got a picture here.
I call this picture 'plant seeds for Joe.'
- [Student] For the next guy.
- Yes, for the next guy.
We're talking about putting
aside retirement money today.
It's just polite to your
elder self, older self.
Put some money aside for...
And what happened today?
I forgot what I was doing.
I was being grateful that my earlier self
did something for me.
The database I guess.
Michael at 30 was getting books
typed in for Michael at 60.
You see what I mean?
And I was thinking, "Good
job Michael at 30. Thank you!
"Thanks for thinking of me.
Thanks for giving me a database."
So it's the same idea here.
When you study emptiness,
it's not just for you.
You're taking care of your future self.
It's like putting aside retirement money.
Your future self will thank you.
And I will challenge you guys.
He said a pretty awesome thing here.
At this point in the text he
said a pretty awesome thing.
He said, "If you do take
care of your future self,
"if you do study emptiness
from the Nagarjuna courses,
then you're taking care
of your future self,"
because...
I'll keep giving you
clues if nobody can guess.
- [Student] If you plant better seeds.
- Come on...
- [student mumbling]
- Yes, even if you were scheduled to die
and go to a world with no dharma,
you will create the dharma in that world.
That's cool.
That's pretty cool. Got it?
What specific practitioner
was he talking about?
- [Student] Self-made.
- Self-made Buddhas. Yes,
self-made Buddhas. Good.
That's amazing. I've never
seen anyone say that so cool.
What's another reason why
you have to study emptiness?
You got to take care of Joe.
Who's Joe? Joe is your next life.
Send him a gift. Send
him some stuff to study
in the next life. And
it's a very sweet feeling
when you consciously do
something for your future self,
like 10 years from now,
and you do something to...
You kind of send a present to
yourself 10 years from now,
but this time you're doing to yourself
a hundred years from now,
a thousand years from now.
And you can make it a Buddhist
practice to do cool things
that send anonymous gifts
to your future self.
That's so cool. That's such a nice idea.
It's like putting chocolate
in drawers at your house
and forgetting about it.
Then later you're like,
"Oh my God, what's in
there? Thank you Michael
three months ago."
That's a cool idea.
What's our time frame here?
I stop at 5:05? Okay, got it.
Plant seeds for Joe. Guess what,
we finished the review of chapter 18.
It's kind of slow but that's our theme.
And that's actually the
most important chapter
that we covered, is 18
on the emptiness of me and mine. Good.
Then we went on to talk about what?
Do you remember chapter 19? Time. Yes.
I was like writing these
review notes for myself,
and I said, "They're going
to have to figure out
"why that order of the
chapters is what it is.
"Maybe I can just give them some hints.
"And I'll give them hints from what
"Choney Lama says in the
opening of the 19th chapter
to connect it to the 18th chapter."
And guess what, he doesn't.
He doesn't even try.
So why you get time coming, an
investigation of time coming
after an investigation of me and mine,
he doesn't even guess.
He just jumps into it.
So it's up to you guys.
If you don't do it...maybe
Choney Lama left it for you.
All right.
We learn some Sanskrit at that point.
Kāla?
- [Student] Time.
- Time. Related to
accelerator, car and all that.
And then in the same class
we went to the next chapter
which was already talking
about convergences of causes
and conditions and the
important word there is hetu.
If you study Buddhist logic,
hetu is the single most important word
and it means 'reason' or 'cause'.
In this discussion it means cause.
But it's extremely important in logic
because it means reason, as a cause.
So we talked about those words.
Then the whole theme of the
time chapter was triads,
groups of three,
GSUM TSAN
The whole theme of the
time chapter was triads.
Do you guys remember the first triad?
- [Student] Yes, it was
like if something exists...
- No, don't make it...
Past, present, future.
Just past, present, future.
And then he said, "Look
when you discuss a triad,
"a natural thing to do
is to compare two to one,
"is not comparing one to one."
If you're talking about three things,
well, how do these two relate to this one?
How do these two relate to this one?
So what is the first two
that it lumps together?
How do the present and
future relate to the past?
And how can the present and
future even relate to the past?
It never touches them. They
never touch each other.
So how did fish relate to green drinks?
Sorry, that's almost connected.
[student Laughing]
JB, give me something random.
[student Mumbling]
How do the javalinas
wandering around on your lawn
relate to green drink?
I mean, they don't a connection.
They can't touch each other.
The present and the future
cannot touch the past,
but without the past, the
present and the future
have no meaning.
They rely on the past.
The present and the
future rest on the past
without touching it.
- That's all just made up in your head.
- Ah, that's correct.
So technically, the
present and the future,
how they happen, is going to
depend on what happened before,
but they have no connection
to what happened before. Why?
- [student mumbling]
- Well that's good. Yes, the past is gone.
How can you have relationship
with somebody who's dead.
I don't know.
Then also what? Point of
contact, point of contact.
What's the point of contact
between nothing and something?
And even if the past did exist now,
and even the present does exist now,
where do they meet?
- [Student] They touch, they
have to be the same thing.
- Yes, if the present touches the past,
then that part of the
past would be the present.
It's messed up. Something
else must be going on.
All right, we had calender
pictures, I don't know.
We don't really need it,
but... You get the point.
He plays with '22 and
'23 depending on '21.
And then says, well do
'21 and '22 depend on '23?
And maybe '21 and '23 need
'22 nested in the middle
to make sense?
He looks at the triads in different ways.
What else did he say
about groups of three?
- [student mumbling]
- Yes, any group of three you ever have,
just use it for that.
I think he gave two examples.
- [Student] Numbers.
- Like one, two, three. Yes.
In fact they were so simple,
I didn't understand the Tibetan.
I was like 'one, two, three?..'
[students and teacher Laughing]
And then he said,
MCHOG DMAN 'BRING
Better, worse, in-between.
Good, bad, in-between.
That they also depend on each other.
But where does good touch in-between?
Because is that part good
or is that part in-between?
They can't touch each other.
If they don't touch each
other you can't compare them,
and you can't say this chocolate
is better than that chocolate.
If they're never in the same
room or in the same mouth.
We'll experiment.
Then he asks a question,
idim R.15, if you got it.
I think it's a person
jumping. And he said,
"Which happens first,
the future or the past?"
- [Student] Both. And one
answer is 'past is first,'
and the other answer is 'future is first.'
- Yes, good, and what's coming up next
is the future. Right?
But then it's the present.
But the time you looked at it, it's past.
So our idea of time is messed up.
I spend a long time
thinking about relativity
and Einstein and stretching
time, shrinking time,
bending time, and it's a lot
easier to understand Einstein
if you read this part,
about the emptiness of time.
Then it makes a lot of sense.
I'll show you another picture, 16.
It's just a personal suggestion.
When you're trying to
understand emptiness better,
instead of using the word self-existent,
it's like trying on
jeans: see what fits you.
I always tell the story that me and V
went to the cowboy store in Cottonwood
and she tried on 42 pairs of jeans
and didn't buy any of them.
And that guy was a little hot.
I went back and bought some
boots just to make him happy.
But try on different words that fit you
and see which one helps you understand it.
The word 'natural' is a good suggestion.
Is it all natural?
Is the way that time
flows part of "nature"?
Or is it artificial?
Is it natural or is it artificial?
You know, they put stuff in candy bars,
is it natural sugar or is it fake sugar?
And just when you're trying to think about
what emptiness means, I
suggest that sometimes
you think about the idea of
natural and what does it mean.
Is the division into past,
present and future natural?
And is the nature of time...
Is time automatically
past, present and future
or is there other ways to look at time?
And I just encourage you to
think about the word natural
instead of self-existing.
By the way I test out words,
like that audience I mentioned,
'China Soft Power' people.
They're very intelligent
business owners, big businesses.
And I say, "Look, let
me ask you something,
"I'm a teacher, I spend a lot
of time, I go around the world
"trying to teach people
and I have a question for you guys."
They're like, "Run it."
I say, "Should I say, karma
or should I say mental seeds?"
And they're like, "Mental
seeds, man, forget karma."
And I was like, I felt so happy
that they can just give
me an honest opinion.
They didn't hesitate at all.
They said, "Oh, f' that. Forget karma.
Don't mention karma.
Just say mental seeds."
So I'm suggesting to you:
think about the word.
Personally, self-existent
doesn't help me at all.
I never walk down the street and say,
"Oh, you're looking at
this self-existent..."
We don't even think of it.
I think one that helps everybody
is 'from its own side'.
"Is that pen coming from its own side?"
'Self-existent' doesn't mean
almost anything to anybody.
But if you say, "Does it
come from its own side?"
Then they say, "Yes, it does."
It's very easy way to get
into emptiness discussion.
And I'm suggesting that
'natural' is a good one too.
Is the division of time
itself into three...
Does it have to be that
way? Is that natural?
Or is it something we made up?
Is it somehow coming from us?
Because the idea of
past, present and future
is so much a part of our life
that we think it must be natural.
I didn't make up past. I
mean, the idea of past,
and the idea of future
and the idea of present,
I didn't make those divisions.
That God made that ort the
world mad that, I don't know.
That was here when I got here.
People were already talking
about yesterday and tomorrow.
And Nagarjuna says, "No, it's not natural.
You did make it."
Personally, I'm interested
that there was a new verb
that I never saw before, it's
called BSNOR BA, B-S-N-O-R
BSNOR BA, so NOR low tone,
N-O-R, means 'to make a mistake',
and then he said, "No
matter which of the triad
you look at depending on the others."
Does '23 depend on '21 and '22?
Does 2023 depend on 2021 and 2022?
Or does 2022 depend '21 and '23?
Or does '21 depend on '22 and '23?
Which is it?
And he says,
"Well, personally, when
I taught it to you guys,
"I started with '21, 2021
"and then I try to show
you how '22 and '23's
relationship depending on that."
But it could've been anything.
We could take anyone and
look at the relationship.
And then he says,
"No matter which two you take together,
and which one you take
separately, BSNOR BA."
- [Student] BSNOR BA.
- Yes, it's a cool verb. It
means there will be an f-up.
It exactly means that. I'm sorry.
You have to add a few letters.
[students laughing]
It means things will
get screwy either way.
Things are going to get screwy.
It's a verb. He made up a new verb.
It's like, it's going to screwify.
Anyway, it's a new word.
For me it's very fascinating,
because I love words.
He says, "Whatever combination you take,
it's all going to screwify you."
Good luck translating that, you guys.
All right, let's look at...
Let's keep going.
We looked at all the triads.
Then he went on a side trip,
and I challenge you guys
to guess what it was.
He finished this idea of threes.
He finished the idea of relativity
of time, which is not...
Relativity is not the same
thing as coming from you.
The fact that how long the past feels
depends on how long the
present and future feels
is not emptiness.
Relativity is not emptiness.
The fact that time with
your girlfriend go slower
because...
That's not emptiness.
Relativity is not emptiness.
It's not true that if there
was no suffering in the world
you couldn't have
pleasure. That's not true.
The idea that this is
dependent origination
which I have heard repeated many times
by 'Vipassana' people,
is totally mistaken.
It doesn't mean that at all.
In that case the Buddha would have to have
a bit of suffering so he
could enjoy his happiness.
It's obviously mistaken.
So emptiness doesn't mean that something
is something only by comparison.
Emptiness means you're
creating all the degrees,
whether you see degrees
or you don't see degrees
in better, worse, medium.
They're all coming from you.
That's the point.
It's not that you can't
have better without worse.
If that's true then you should
just jump off a building
because you can't have happiness.
You can't have pure happiness.
You'd have to go out and
get a dose of unhappiness
so you could appreciate your
happiness, something like that.
Then why am I talking
about like that, I forgot.
- [Student] Side trip.
- Yes, what is his side trip?
What? Guess. He's talking about time
and he's going on to his next chapter.
He's ready to go on to his next chapter,
but he wants to say a
little bit more about time.
He presents other people's ideas of time.
He stops and takes a break.
He said, "Hey, you want to
know what the non-Buddhist
"in ancient India thought about time?
"Or you want to know what
the lower Buddhist schools
thought about time?"
And he goes off like that.
That's a popular strategy for Nagarjuna.
He often will compare his concepts
to the concepts of other
traditions in his culture,
which was Hindu, Jain, other traditions.
Many. 'Mīmāṃsā'.
And then he'll say, "By the way,
and lower Buddhist
schools think like this."
And then he'll give you more confidence
about what your school is by
describing other traditions.
So here's the first one.
Somebody came from another
tradition and said,
"I don't know why you have
all this trouble with time
"because we have definitions of time.
"We have seconds. We have
minutes. We have hours.
"We have weeks. We have
months. We have centuries.
"We have millenia. What's the problem?
"We've got units of time.
They may be artificial
"but they're fixed.
An hour is 60 minutes.
A month is 30, 28 days"
Well, he says, "A year is 12
months. It may be made up.
"It may be an artifice, but it's fixed.
"You don't have to stress
so much about time,
"being compared to the
other times and other...
They have a definition."
And he says,
"Oh, oh, what's the definition?"
- One minute is 60.
- So what's a second?
- A second is like 60
milliseconds, 1000 milliseconds.
That's all, 1000 milliseconds.
He says, "Well, oh, I see. So
your years are based on months?"
- Yeah, you got it.
- And the months are based on days?
- The days on hours?
- Got it.
- And seconds on milliseconds.
- How long is a millisecond?
And then the guy is like,
"Well, you know it's just <dip>."
And he says, "Oh, <dip>."
And then Nagarjuna is like, "How
many <dips> inside the <dips>?"
And the guy says, "We
know the dip, dip thing,
dip, dip, dip %thing."
And then he says, "Well,
how many dips, dips, dips,
in the dip, dip?"
And he says, "Well, you
just cut it down to the
shortest moment of time and
then you grab that one."
He says, "You can't."
BZUNG DUS MED PA means you can't grab it.
It's too short for perception.
You can't perceive it.
If you get a measurement of time
which is too short to perceive,
what does it mean to a human being
who is a perceiving animal?
Then it's just you making up stuff.
Now you're just making up stuff.
He says, "I agree you can
define a day as so many seconds,
but what do you define as a second?"
The guy says, "There
are many milliseconds."
And he says, "What about
the parts of that?"
The guy says, "But you
can't perceive that."
He says, "What does it mean
to have 50 non perceivables
"and 60 non perceivables and
then 300 non perceivables?
"Don't you realize it's all BS?
"You're piling up zeros and
saying it's 50. Got it?"
Because you can't define the littlest one,
because you can't perceive it any more,
because it doesn't have a...
- [Student] Front end and back end.
- Front end and back end. Yes.
It would be nice, your third
book from today's conversation,
should be front ends and back ends.
I was thinking you could...
Well, anyway, we can talk
about that photo on the front..
[student laughing]
By the way, here's the picture of...
Those milliseconds just
kind of run away, fly away.
You can't define them. You can't...
BZUNG DUS MED PA means
they cannot be....'perceptio'.
They cannot be grasped,
perceived. They cannot be.
You can't hold them.
You can't define them.
You can't touch them.
Your comforting units of
time were made up of zeros.
And you're piling them
up and saying it's 50,
but it's still 50 zeros.
That's all.
We want to go deeper?
- [Students] Yay!
- How much time we've got?
- [Student] Five minutes.
- We still have five?
Having talked about the
other traditions of his time,
which by the way, whenever
you see that in scripture,
I'll tell you a clue. You can
pretty much fill in 'science.'
You don't have to say Jainism
or Samkya system or Mimamsa,
or Charvaka, you can just say scientist,
because they're as crude and wrong
as the non-Buddhist
schools 2000 years ago.
Just fill in the name
'science,' it's okay.
So he says, "Okay, we
wiped out the scientists.
Who else we've got?"
"What about the lower Buddhist schools?"
"Yes, what about the functionalists?"
These are the three lower schools.
They say something interesting.
Time is measurable and time is definable
because you can link it to a
physical object like the moon,
the phases of the moon or the sun setting
and the sun coming up.
There are physical things in the world
and you can tie time to
them and say that's a day.
When the sun comes up and
when the sun goes down,
that half circle is a day.
So the functionalists,
the Buddhist schools say,
"We can define time in certain units
"because we can tie those times,
"we can tie the theory of time
to physical objects in the
world that we can watch."
So it takes 30 days for the
moon to shrink and come back,
and that's fixed amount of time.
You can just say that way.
And then he says, "Oh, so..."
Here it's a little bit subtle.
I told you we're going to go deeper,
and that's may be the
last thing we do here.
Anybody want to guess what Nagarjuna says?
I'll give you a clue.
The lower Buddhist
guys, they come and say,
"Look, time is definable externally."
- Why?
- You can link it to a physical event
like the change of the moon
or the appearance of the...
or the stars circling by the next season,
certain constellations come back.
These are the three traditional
Vinaya measures of time,
which are lunar, solar and stellar.
And Vinaya has all three. It's
very beautiful, but anyway.
Last thing today.
I'll say it again. Lower Buddhist schools:
"We can define time because
we can take a physical
"thing that we can see in
the sky and we can link that
"to the thing called
day or night, or month,
"or season of the constellations.
"No problem. That's not artificial."
Okay, last thing.
$100. How does Nagarjuna argue back?
I'll say it again.
They say, measurements of
time can be fixed objectively,
because you can tie them to
the motion of planetary bodies.
I'll give you a clue.
- [Student] They can't connect.
- The connection is coming from you.
The decision to connect to
that is coming from you.
So the whole thing is coming from you.
Got it?
If one part of the whole
thing is coming from you,
then it's coming from you.
- Is there a sun moving in
the sky in a certain way?
- Maybe.
- Is there words called
minutes, hours, days? Yes.
- Do the words hours,
minutes, days make sense
without reference to a physical body?
- No. You've got to have a physical body.
- Okay. So, it's artificial?
- No, it's not.
- Yes, it is.
- Why?
- You decided what to connect to what.
You decided what to connect to what.
Therefore, it's coming from you. Got it?
Who made a 100$? Rosa, yes.
- [Student] Rosa.
- I think it was Rosa.
We brought into question
the very concept of time itself.
And that's going to naturally
lead into a discussion of the time
it takes for results to come
out of collections of causes
and conditions and then
that's going to naturally
relate to how do things
come into existence
and how do things leave existence.
So there's a flow there. If you heard me,
you can do part of your homework.
And again, I just encourage you to...
I agree that studying emptiness all day
and not helping people in need,
not helping refugees or poor people
or people who are at war...
I agree that that's unwise
and that you're probably
not developing spiritually. I agree.
And I agree that if you have no compassion
or love for other people
then you're failure
in your spiritual... I agree.
And I agree that if you're
not doing your exercise
and your yoga or things like that,
you are going to hurt
yourself. You can't just sit
and study emptiness all day. I agree.
But if you don't spend some quality time,
and I keep saying that
to my close friends.
They say, "Oh, Geshe-la,
I look at the books
once a while, I'm okay."
And I say, "Yes, but do
you give it quality time?
Do you give it your..."
For me my quality time is
like 8:00AM to 11:00AM.
That's the quality time.
And I say, "Do you consciously
give it your quality time?"
And they say, "Well, I don't know."
So, what I'm saying is studying emptiness
is not the only thing to
do to become a good person,
but it's a necessary part
of becoming a good person.
And if you skip it because
it seems intellectual,
then you're making a huge mistake.
You got to use the parts of your mind
that are not your physical
senses to see deeper things.
You have to develop your mind
as a instrument of perception
to see deeper things.
If you don't practice
thinking about emptiness,
you won't see emptiness.
It's not possible. It won't happen.
This a muscle also. You
got to exercise your eyes.
There's a yoga exercising with
your eyes. Do you know that?
- [Students] Yes.
- You go like this. It actually helps.
And you can develop your hearing.
You can work out in the gym.
But to think that you don't
have to exercise your mind
to have a happy life is big mistake.
So dig into these ideas.
The big, big break-throughs
are with friends.
And that's why Buddhist monks
spend two, three hours a day
in a debate ground.
And you see pictures of the form,
of the people jumping
around and screaming,
but the big break-throughs are
the whispered conversations
in the hours after, in the debate ground.
The people sit down and they're like,
"God, I don't get it,"
and the other guy says,
"I don't get it either,"
and then third guy says,
"I kind of got it."
And then you see these
movies of debates, right?
But there is a big part
of the debate ground
where you sit down, when
you're all exhausted
and you start talking. We are in the dark.
We are in the star light
and it's so beautiful.
You just start saying,
"Could you really get that
thing? I didn't get it."
So it's crucial that you
meet with your friends.
You meet with other students.
Don't talk about stupid, useless things.
If you want to be the Bodhisattva
in your group of friends,
you be the one who,
when the conversation at
dinner starts to deteriorate
into politics or some gossip,
then say, "God, what did you
think about that chapter 21,
did you get it?"
And it's so fun. You will
trigger a conversation.
And it's nice to be the one who secretly
triggers the conversation.
So, try to be that kind of person who,
when you're with your friends,
especially your dharma
friends, try to secretly
push the conversation to
something about emptiness
or something meaningful.
That's a wonderful skill.
That should be one of the perfections:
how to push the conversation
to something useful.
So do that and if you do that
you will understand Nagarjuna.
And luckily we will have
a couple more sessions
of Nagarjuna.
See you then.
Yay!
[students auplauding]